Inventory of the Walker Peyton Moncure Papers, 1868-1962
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Walker Peyton Moncure papers
1868-1962
Moncure, Walker Peyton, 1877-1964
00599
3 cubic ft. (5 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Photographs, papers, and artifacts of a storekeeper on the Nothern Cheyenne Indian Reservation, who also ranched in Wyoming and speculated in oil on the Crow Reservation in Montana.
Biography of Walker Peyton Moncure
Walker Peyton Moncure (1877-1964) was a rancher, petroleum investor, and owner of a general store in Busby, on the Northern Cheyenne Indian Reservation in southeastern Montana. Moncure became a friend of Two Moon, a Cheyenne who participated in the Battle of Little Bighorn. Two Moon died in 1917 and Moncure had him reburied at Busby, erecting a monument for him. Moncure sold his store to join the Merchant Marine during World War I. He then homesteaded in Wyoming and speculated in oil on the Crow Reservation in Montana. In 1929 Moncure bought back the Busby store, which he continued to operate into the 1940s. Moncure organized festivals, some of which he called "Sun Dances," for his Cheyenne customers. In 1931, Moncure built what became known as the “Moncure Tipi,” a structure that became a site of tribal give-away ceremonies and dances. In addition, it housed Civilian Conservation Corps work crews during the 1930s construction of the Busby School. The structure was added to the National Register of Historic Places in 2002.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, legal documents, and printed material concerning the Two Moon burial monument, Walker Moncure's life, All American Indian Days, and petroleum drilling on the Crow Indian Reservation in Montana. Also included are photographs of the Northern Cheyenne (Tongue River) Indian Reservation and of Moncure's store in Busby, Montana, as well as artifacts from the store. In addition there is a typescript of Moncure's unpublished novel "The Throwbacks," based on his experiences as an Indian trader. There are also publicity materials for "Sun Dances" sponsored by Moncure.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Walker Peyton Moncure at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
This material was received from Walker Peyton Moncure, 1958-1962
Access Terms
Two Moon, 1847-1917; All American Indian Days; Oil fields -- Montana; Cheyenne Indians; Northern Cheyenne Indian Reservation (Mont.); Crow Indian Reservation (Mont.); Busby (Mont.)
Mines and Mineral Resources; Native Americans; Politics, Government, and Law; Montana
Container List
- Series I. Documents and Photographs
  - All American Indian Days (printed material), 1957-1958 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Information on W.P. Moncure, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Legal Documents, 1912-1947 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - Sinclair, F.H. (includes photographs of All American Indian Days), 1957 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence - University of Wyoming (regarding Moncure collection), 1958-1962 (Box 1)
  - Indians (printed material), circa 1950s (Box 1)
  - Manuscript - "Love Me More", circa 1959 (Box 1)
  - Manuscript - "The Throwbacks", circa 1958 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1943-1960 (Box 1)
  - Oil Field - Beauvais (Montana), 1921-1922 (Box 1)
  - Oil Field - Crow Indian Reservation (Montana), 1921-1923, 1941 (Box 1)
  - Oil Field - Soap Creek (Montana), 1921 (Box 1)
  - Oil Field - Woody Creek (Montana), 1921-1923 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets (George Washington; Custer Fight; devotional), 1868-1958 (Box 1)
  - Photograph Album - Northern Cheyenne Indian Reservation (Tongue River) and Crow Reservation, 1910s-1920s (Box 1)
  - Photographs (W. P. Moncure; Busby store; Two Moon monument; etc.), circa 1910s (Box 1)
  - Post Cards and Greeting Cards, 1934-1957 (Box 1)
  - Program - Cheyenne Frontier Days, 1951 (Box 1)
  - Two Moon Monument - "Indian Trader's Cache" by Kathryn Wright, in Montana Magazine (includes correspondence and photographs), 1957 (Box 1)
  - Two Moon Monument - Wright, Kathryn (correspondence and clipping), 1953-1957 (Box 1)
  - Two Moon Monument and White Bull Monument (James D. King letter and enclosures), 1956-1957 (Box 1)
  - White Buffalo (clipping and post card), undated (Box 1)
- Series II. Posters
  - "Cheyenne Indian Sun Dance at Busby", undated (Box 3)
  - "Cowboy Days - Indian Nights" Sun Dance (chromolithograph), undated (Box 3)
  - "4th of July on the Rosebud", undated (Box 3)
  - "On the Move" by C.H. Russell (chromolithograph), undated (Box 3)
  - "Unveiling of Two Moon Monument at Busby", undated (Box 3)
- Series III. Artifacts
  - Beadwork Belts (2) - probably Cheyenne, undated (Box 3)
  - Blanket - Navajo (33"x48"; red, brown, and black geometric patterns on white background), undated (Box 5)
  - Jewelry Box - Brazil(?) (wood with painted glass cover over butterfly wings, depicting parrot and palm tree), circa 1950s (Box 4)
  - Moccasins - Cheyenne (2 pairs) - beaded (worn by W.P. Moncure), undated (Box 3)
  - Pipe (red pipestone, broken in two pieces), undated (Box 4)
  - Pouches - probably Cheyenne (2) - beaded leather, undated (Box 3)
  - Shawl - embroidered (imported for Busby store from India or Czechoslovakia), undated (Box 3)